This is Wyatt, and on today's episode, I was joined by Isha Varshney, Head of Ecosystem
at Sellout Foundation.
We talked at length about digital money usage in Sub-Saharan Africa and global stablecoin
adoption patterns.
I hope you enjoy our conversation.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures.
All of these expressed by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions
and do not reflect the opinions of Castle Island Ventures.
Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed in this podcast.
You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific inducement
to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy, but only as an expression
of their personal opinion.
This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Brought down by bad mortgage investments, Lehman, which has 25,000 employees, will be
liquidated.
The federal government loans American International Group AIG $85 billion.
This is a different kind of market and the Fed is asleep.
The federal government is stepping in to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the two mortgage
giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy
with a new round of quantitative easing.
You print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry.
So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin.
Bitcoin.
Isha, thanks for joining us on the podcast.
Excited to talk to you today.
Thank you for having me.
I'm really excited about our conversation today.
I'm excited to be into a couple of really fun things that we've chatted about earlier.
Me as well.
If you don't mind, please give a bit of a personal background and talk about what you're
doing these days.
Happy to.
My name is Isha Varshney.
I head Ecosystem at Sallow Foundation.
Sallow for people that are not aware is an EBM layer two blockchain and I've been head
of Ecosystem here for two years and then I was hired to be head of DeFi.
Prior to this, I have a really interesting background, very not crypto native.
So did traditional finance before this.
I'm an accountant by profession, did M&A at a KPMG for a few years, did an MBA.
I did what everybody does typically after the MBA, went into traditional finance and
private equity.
But the interesting thing about all of this is that I'm actually born and raised in Kenya.
After MBA, I went back home for a couple of holidays to see my parents and there was this
massive fintech revolution happening on the continent, specifically in that region of
the world.
I had friends that had never been to Kenya, moving to Kenya to do all of these really
cool interesting fintech jobs and I was like, oh shit, I think I'm missing out and I never
done tech before.
So I just rolled the dice, took a sabbatical for three months and I joined a regional bank
that was setting up the digital banking unit and that was my first foray into tech.
We set up the digital bank and the product is still a market leader in that region and
then did a bunch of fintech consulting work.
You name it from lending to wealth advisory to like payments and that helped me understand
what building a product and building a team in the tech space looks like, post which
I had my own startup obviously as you do when you work in tech, you have to do something
of your own.
So I have a wealth tech robot advisory startup that was successfully bought out in a few
years.
This was, think of it like the Acorn, those few that are familiar.
It was very similar to the Acorn, focused in the Indian market and that did really well
so did that.
And then once I got bought out, it was also COVID, had just moved to America, wasn't allowed
to work because of regulations around re-immigration here and so had this period of what am I doing?
What is the next iteration of technology and then also what is the next iteration of finance?
Because I went from traditional finance to fintech and then obviously DeFi was the next
obvious move.
And so I joined Solo as head of DeFi like I mentioned and at that point we just announced
something called DeFi for the People.
It was a hundred million dollar allocation to liquidity and grants and just encouraging
the DeFi ecosystem in Solo.
And then as luck would have it, FTX happened straight after I joined.
And so that hundred million dollar evaporated very, very quickly.
But I think in my mind, excellent timing because I learned how to build in the bear.
I've been in the ecosystem during the bear.
Oh, we're only going to do DeFi.
Oh, what is actual utility?
What is product market fit for Web3?
And that's been a really interesting journey, especially at Solo because Solo was built
for the real world.
We're constantly thinking about not only the crypto native community per se, but we're
thinking about how do we onboard users in emerging markets.
So when our typical user is somebody sitting in Kenya, in Nigeria, and also given my background,
it's really interesting to me because then we're thinking about, oh, what do these people
need?
How do we bring them on chain and bring them on chain in a way that we abstract the technology
away?
How do we make it easier for them to interact on chain without them knowing they're interacting
on chain?
And what is product market fit for this user base?
And so we'll talk a little bit more around how the ecosystem is built around a couple
of things that I'm really passionate about.
But yeah, that's a little bit of my background and how I ended up at Solo.
You have a very holistic financial markets background, which is helpful for this subject.
What did you see in Kenya when you mentioned that financial revolution you talked about?
And when was this also?
So Kenya is a really interesting market.
We're talking about 2016, 2017.
M-Pesa is just starting up and it's just proliferating the market.
And so you're thinking about in Nairobi, even today, I just carry my phone and I know that's
happening more and more in the U.S. where you use Apple Pay everywhere.
But in Nairobi, I've been doing this for years.
You just take your phone and you have M-Pesa on your phone and then that's it.
You don't carry your wallet and you can make every single payment through M-Pesa.
And in that region on the M-Pesa app, you have robo-advisory on the M-Pesa app, you
have insurance on the M-Pesa app.
Your whole world.
It's like a super app.
It's become this super app system, but it just started with payments.
And so all your payments happen through M-Pesa.
Can you talk about what M-Pesa is for the audience?
M-Pesa is mobile money.
It's run by Safaricom.
It was essentially started as mobile money.
What they saw in Nairobi and in Kenya and a couple of different countries was getting
access to fiat was difficult.
So people started trading airtime, literally airtime, minutes on their phone.
Mostly people in the US and the developed world have plans and you don't think about
minutes on your phone or data minutes.
But people started trading data minutes and they were like, oh, wow, this is interesting.
We can make this into a currency.
It's the literal utility token.
Literally the utility token.
So they made it into a currency and they got nominated into the dollar, into the Kenya
Shillings or the dollar.
It's literally mobile money.
So I can send you mobile money as actual currency.
It started with airtime.
It went into digitization of their currency.
So that's M-Pesa and it started with just the payment system.
And then I think the beauty of this system was why it really shot up was you have this
mobile money on your phone, but if you want cash for it, there's little vendors, little
stalls everywhere that you can go and it's similar to the off-ramping problem that we
have currently in Web3.
You can go to these kiosks, they're called there.
Then every little shop is a kiosk and you can go to the kiosk and say, hey, I have this
much M-Pesa.
Can you give me cash?
There's usually a spread for it.
And so most people don't want to off-ramp into actual cash, but you can do it if you
want.
And then even to on-ramp, you can go give them cash and then they can give you M-Pesa.
And how much do you need cash given that M-Pesa is in the system?
Today, zero.
Every single person takes cash.
When you think about micropayments in Kenya, at least the way I think about micropayments
in Kenya, I'm not talking about the coffees and the food and stuff like that.
I'm thinking about the guy that is taking money for parking.
And so it's not ticketed like this as an actual person that's taking money for parking.
It's 10 or 20 shillings.
It's a very minimal amount.
120 shillings is one dollar.
So I'm talking about 10 or 20 shillings.
It's nothing.
It's fractions of the dollar.
And then even that person will take M-Pesa.
So every single person you interact with will take M-Pesa.
The guy who's selling you tea and tea there is in a little stall on the road selling it
on a little stool while sitting on another little stool.
Even he'll take M-Pesa.
So I don't remember the last time I saw the shilling as a note, but that's just me.
And so it's ubiquitous in that region with that because you digitize this.
You digitize money.
With that came so many interesting use cases.
With that, the fact that you could scan your phone records, scan your SMS, and every time
you do an M-Pesa transaction, you get an SMS saying, oh, a hundred shilling deposited
or 200 shilling taken out of your account.
I could then, as a fintech, just ask you for the digital records of your messages and understand
your entire financial history.
I'm not asking a bank for your financial statement.
I'm literally asking you for messages.
And so it opens up so many different use cases.
For instance, lending became really popular.
Peer-to-peer lending?
Fintech lending.
For a retail user, money in that region is really, really expensive.
I remember there was a period of time where I've seen with my own self, 20% per month
is the rate of interest that you're paying and it accumulates.
You can imagine what that number becomes.
On an annualized basis, it's a ridiculous number if you're paying 20% interest per month.
But this allowed other players to go in and say, oh, actually, we can lend money to you.
The rates at which they were lending money wasn't competitive to what you get money at
from a bank in the U.S., but to the public in general on the ground over there, they
were like, oh, wow, this is so much cheaper.
And that's why fintech lending became so big there because you could do M-Pesa transactions.
Even e-commerce became a thing there because you digitize money and the minute you digitize
money, and we are all talking about this in the crypto ecosystem, but the minute you digitize
money, so much more is possible.
And I'm talking like 2015, 10 years from today.
So it was a really interesting period to see that transition.
Another thing to maybe mention for your audience, and I'm sure they're not aware of this.
In the U.S., you can go into any bank and say, I want a retail banking account.
Most can kind of go in and say, hey, I want a retail banking account.
In some parts of the world, especially Sub-Saharan Africa, retail banking is not a profitable
business.
So even to get a bank account is really, really difficult.
So what do you love with when you're hoarding cash in your house and crime levels are so
high?
It's so revolutionary because you're like, oh, now I get access to banking without actually
having to go to a bank.
And it's funny when I was working at the bank, I was like, oh, wow, we're going to set up
a retail banking unit.
So now we providing access to retail banking to a large part of the population.
And what we saw was your salary would sweep into your account and there was an instant
sweep out.
Literally instant where they sweep the entire monthly salary out into the M-Pesa wallet.
So even when you gave them a bank account, because it had been so many years without
banking, they were like, okay, we prefer the M-Pesa system.
So that's an interesting part of the world.
So I'm going to play this skeptic for a second, which is if M-Pesa works, why does currency
need to be on chain?
Because M-Pesa is not on chain.
M-Pesa works, yes, but it works only in Kenya.
And people are trying to replicate the M-Pesa use case across even African countries and
it hasn't picked up for many different reasons.
M-Pesa works because you have this massive kiosk system that are on and off-run providers.
That system isn't there anywhere else in the world.
It's like Binance P2P.
Exactly like Binance.
Why is Binance so prolific in one specific region and not the others?
It's because of the P2P.
You have to know that you have access to your money and at a given point in time, and that's
why M-Pesa works.
Why are we digitizing?
So even with M-Pesa, and we're seeing a lot of stable coin usage in Kenya, and we can
talk about that a little bit more, but we're seeing a lot of stable coin usage in Kenya
is because the M-Pesa is pegged to the shilling and the shilling as a currency against the
dollar is not necessarily the strongest currency.
And that's why you need to digitize and getting access to dollars is more important in a lot
of the world than most of us understand.
So given that M-Pesa has worked because of those vendors who will offer redemption, do
you think that is the unlock to mobile money systems, whether on-chain or otherwise in
other markets?
Or do you think there will be institutionalized on-ramping, off-ramping, which will happen
first?
That's a really good question.
It depends on which markets.
You think it'll be different in each one?
I think it'll depend on every market.
Also, I think we were talking about 2015.
Technologies move so much.
I want to say 70% of my personal financial transactions happen online now as opposed
to actually physical interactions.
So if you don't have off-ramping in the physical world, not so critical now.
But again, depends on which country and which region.
I'm sure some of the emerging markets having vendors and offering providers on the ground,
little kiosks everywhere, will be critical for mass adoption.
But that's just my take.
Who knows?
Yeah, it's interesting because it's always hard to imagine here in the U.S.
And I guess the reason for that is because each leg of our transaction is handled.
We have Venmo for peer-to-peer and we have payment at a storefront.
But getting cash is still arguably a bit more of a pain than it should be in my life, for
example.
I don't know if you've the same experience.
I don't remember the last time I used cash to be honest.
But again, I mean, you're removing cash from your financial transactions completely in
the U.S. and in some of the more developed world.
But cash is king in a lot of countries even now.
And so in those countries where cash is king and where you're actually doing a lot of daily
transactions in cash, you still need off-ramp providers that will go from any Web3 currency
or even stablecoin to cash so that at least having that as an option is important to onboard
users.
And then eventually when all your transactions and all your financial transactions go online
or on-chain, then it won't matter.
I've also learned that consumer behavior changes very quickly if it's convenient and inexpensive.
If it reduces cost, time, effort, consumer behavior is easier to change than you would
think.
Definitely.
Especially if there's not a great alternative.
So given that experience set, did Celo find you or did you find Celo or how did that come
about?
I tell people this job was made for me.
So I was exploring Web3 and I did this fellowship program that Gitcoin used to run called Kernel
and one of the co-founders of Celo came to give an intro to Celo, just what he thought
about Web3.
He wasn't even talking about Celo, he was talking about Web3 and the Mycelium network
and things like that.
And if you've ever heard Sebs, he's one of the co-founders of Celo.
If you've ever heard any of his talks, you will have heard Mycelium and how everything
is interconnected and how financial systems are all interconnected and how we need to
generate this whole new world where we think differently from the existing structures.
And so he came on and I was like, well, that's a really good way to think about financial
systems and how we can reimagine financial systems.
And the Celo team was also doing this Kernel cohort.
And so I reached out to them once he came on and I was like, oh, I'd love to learn more.
And they were like, oh, cool.
Let's reach out.
And they were like, oh, you have a bunch of developing country experience and we're looking
for someone.
Would you consider interviewing?
And the rest, as I say, is history.
It's a great fit.
I know the regions that we target really well and work in those regions.
So it's like a really great fit.
Mycelium exposure is the extent of a Netflix documentary called Fantastic Fungi, but I'll
have to get up to speed on the financial network side of it.
He describes it similar to how financial networks could be like the Fungi network, how it's
all APEC connected.
Did I buy that?
It's an interesting conversation.
So what was Celo's mission when you joined and how has it evolved or stayed the same?
So we're very mission focused chain and our mission is prosperity for all.
And I don't think we've changed the mission.
So when you think about prosperity for all, everybody has a different take on this and
you could have prosperity for all.
So the way I kind of understand it is prosperity for all translates into financial inclusion
just because I'm a finance background.
To me, I take it in from a financial perspective, but prosperity for all from a different perspective
is also very refi.
And so the Celo mission is essentially built and designed for real world adoption of Web3
that unlocks this mission of prosperity for all.
And when you think about real world adoption, because the chain we thought about emerging
markets as a really big part of the world, the chain is built in a way that is focused
on inclusivity.
So we're very mobile first.
So all applications with Celo are mobile focused.
We have things such as fee abstraction.
So gas in the ecosystem can be paid in stablecoins because we understand.
My first crypto transaction didn't go through and I was sweating because I was like, oh,
why is this not going through?
And then I realized, oh, I need another token for gas.
But if you're in this ecosystem or when you're onboarding to this ecosystem, let's suppose
you have only one wallet and there's stablecoin on that wallet, you shouldn't be able to do
the transaction with just the stablecoin.
And that's the thought behind Celo.
OK, you can have one wallet, but just a USDT or a USDC.
And then the transaction will go through because you can pay for gas.
So fee extraction is a really big thing.
There's ultra green money, which is inbuilt into the chain, which is essentially like
portion allocation of the gas fee goes towards carbon offsetting.
Like I mentioned, phone number mapping is really important because we think most of
the world interacts with technology through their mobile phone as opposed to like a browser
or laptop.
The chain is built for, like I said, everyday use, everyday user, but also the technology
is really frontier.
We were the first POS chain and we're at this really cool intersection of frontier tech
and real world use case.
And I think that's where Celo will always remain.
I'm curious how you guys look at the balance given you're in the stablecoin space at a
global level between trying to provide better native systems for people globally versus
some would say there's value to offering dollars to people globally as an alternative to their
local financial systems.
So how do you strike the balance and which if one of the two is more mission aligned
with what you guys are doing?
That's a really good question.
I don't think we are picking a side because I don't think there's a side to be picked.
You need dollars in the world and access to dollars is really important for users in
specific countries.
Nigeria, for instance, is a really good example for that, where your currency kind of
fluctuates on a weekly basis.
It's a 20, 30 percent fluctuation on a weekly basis.
All of us talk about Bitcoin to be the store of value, but actually, for some people in
the world, dollars are the store of value.
So having nominated stablecoins is really important in an ecosystem.
And so, like I mentioned, we have native USDC and USDT and CUSD as dollar denominated
stablecoins that are all gas currencies in the ecosystem.
But it's interesting when you provide access to dollars, then a lot of really interesting
cool applications get built on top of it and then users then want to go, OK, so if
dollars are store of value, but we actually need to do everyday transactions.
And so you need their local currencies for everyday transactions.
So currently in the ecosystem, we have, I think, 22 plus native stablecoins.
And then I think that's between 12 to 14 different currencies.
And so a user can store value in dollar, but then can move that to their local currency
and then use it for everyday transactions.
And then the other thing that I think most of us don't think about is if you just have
dollars in any ecosystem, then how does lending happen?
Because if you're in markets where your local currency evaluates on a regular basis,
then not only are you paying interest on that loan, you're also paying currency
fluctuation, which becomes really expensive sometimes to definitely local currencies
for some of these interesting use cases like lending.
Have you historically faced any pushback from nations or local regulators when
you're potentially offering dollars to people globally?
Not yet. We're also committed to working with jurisdictions in every region that we
operate and we've prioritized for compliance and benefits of users.
But to be honest, we are not a stablecoin issuer per se, we're just an ecosystem
where stablecoins that are issued by other entities live within our ecosystem.
Yeah, that makes sense.
We're also really committed to making sure that we do our due diligence when
anything launches in our ecosystem to make sure that they're talking to regulators
or in specific conversations with them.
Why do you think non-USD stablecoins haven't emerged at broader scale yet?
Depends on what you think is broader scale.
So firstly, there were not so many non-USD stablecoins a year ago.
I think a lot more issuers are issuing non-USD stablecoins within the last six to
12 months. I've seen a lot more non-USD stablecoins.
I also think that what is the product market fit for non-USD stablecoins is
lending and the FX markets.
And for some of this to be true, it becomes a world in which you have to make sure
that there's a lot of depth of liquidity for this to make sense at all.
And you have to explain to the world what the use cases for this are.
So when you think about FX, when I used to live in, for instance, Africa, when I
was working in Africa, if you needed to go from the shilling to the Guinean CD,
you had to go shilling dollar and then you would spread there and then dollars
Guinean CD. But now there's on-chain stablecoins where you can go directly.
Mento Protocol is in protocol in the ecosystem, which is doing a lot of FX.
They were on the podcast last week.
That's perfect. I love that team.
They're a really great team.
And I'm sure they talked about how you can go from one currency to the other
without going through the dollar and things like that.
I think are revolutionary.
I just don't think the world's caught on yet.
I think with some of this patience is important.
We're a little bit ahead of what people are thinking about long term.
And again, depth of liquidity is really important.
So for this to be relevant and true, you would need institutional capital
providers to come in and deepen liquidity.
And I don't think that's happened yet.
And I think they're coming slowly, slowly.
They're looking at all of this slowly.
Yeah, I agree. I think it'll be lucrative.
It's so great. It's all on chain.
Host of transacting is what?
Nothing. Gas is nothing.
And spreads are incredible.
And it's also twenty four seven.
The effects markets on chain are twenty four seven.
Imagine trading that can happen.
Do you guys have an interest in also pursuing non fiat
nominated stable coins or stable coin flat coin like products
that might be tied to real estate or equities or other asset classes like that?
I think those are really interesting.
I remember the promise of RWAs early days of all of this tokenization of their assets.
Again, for some of this, I really believe truly that liquidity is a key driver.
Am I going to tokenize a random mining asset and I'm expecting retail to buy it?
No, not really.
I think retail will buy a small slice in that whole bar.
So with the institutional capital providers looking at Web 3, more scrutiny here in Web 3,
more liquidity coming to Web 3, I think would make all of these things interesting.
Like I said, on chain markets are twenty four seven,
which is not the case in any other markets.
So I think it'll be good to have tokenized versions of these assets.
But who's buying these assets is really important to look at.
From what we're seeing,
it feels like the remittance apps will be an early catalyst
and that all of a sudden you'll have real inflections in volume of different stable coins.
And once you have that, that starts to tease in the liquidity providers
because they're like, OK, it's going to be lucrative
if I can take the other side of this very hefty trade.
And then maybe they'll stick around and start to stand up other markets.
Because the point you made, you can literally stand up FX markets,
which will be high volume relative to an amount of liquidity provided
and should be a high return.
Absolutely. Just speaking of remittance,
I want to say remittance is a use case.
In my mind is the perfect product market fit for Web 3 where we are right now
and stable coins for where we are right now.
To give you an example, we talked about Africa Focus for so much,
and we haven't talked about one of our main products, which is Opera Mini Pay.
It's a collaboration with Opera, which is a browser product.
We integrated a stable coin wallet into the browser
and we've onboarded seven million plus users on that browser product.
It's a stable coin only wallet.
So you could only have USDC, USDT and CUSD on that wallet.
Seven million plus people have onboarded to it.
And then recently we went and like made it into a standalone apps.
It's currently available for all of you on Android or iOS and you can download it.
And in my mind, that will be the biggest catalyst for cross border remittance.
I mean, to be honest, the other day I sent my mom just on Mother's Day.
I couldn't find flowers online and it was really late at night.
But I'd forgotten Mother's Day.
I'm not a great daughter.
Just sent her some money saying, hey, can you please buy yourself flowers today?
It's super simple. It settled in one second.
It was great. And I'm talking about a really trivial use case.
But remittance just in and out of Africa is double digit a million on an annual basis.
And so if you can capture even a slice of this market, that's big money.
We've done cross border remittance of the traditional sons in and out of Africa.
It takes seven days sometimes through the banking network.
And the spreads are ridiculous.
And if you're doing this on stable coins, you have no spreads.
It's cents on the dollar for gas and then you're done.
So I'm really excited about the MiniPay standalone app.
I would imagine a lot of the remittance piece gets captured in there.
I was going to touch on opera.
So you brought it up in timely fashion with your business background.
Do you think adoption will be more so through an opera or a finance
or yellow card product that to some degree are accounts that are a little bit more free form
where they give you access and it's a little bit of do what you like with it
or more of a transfer wise Felix type experience where it's a purpose
built remittance product that links with existing accounts.
So it's funny. You've mentioned opera, finance and yellow card as competitors.
But it's interesting that opera actually uses yellow card and finance for on and off.
I meant a group, though.
I shouldn't say I don't think they're competitors.
I think they have parallels.
They're all like bundled into one product for some of your audience
that may not be familiar in some of the markets that we're talking about.
When you show somebody a dollar,
when you show them a dollar fiat currency, they don't know what that is.
For them, dollar is USDT.
Really, in Nigeria, there's some areas where they think of dollar as USDT.
In these areas, do I think the transfer wise will come on top?
Maybe not.
Do I think products like opera will come on top?
Absolutely. So it depends market to market.
But I also think that this market is so big, there is space for everybody to play.
It's also just a world in which a lot of this money movement.
It's a bunch of trust.
So opera specifically, I think they're well positioned
because they have trust with the users from their browser product already.
It's not a brand new branding going into the market and saying,
hey, users for cross border remittance, people trust them.
So I think we have a really good finding chance.
But I also think that there's space for everybody to play.
This is a big market.
I think if transfer wise comes up tomorrow, and I don't know if they're already doing it,
I'm sure they're looking at this already.
But if transfer wise comes up tomorrow and says, hey, we'll do cross border remittance
through stable coins, I think there's a world in which everybody plays in this market.
Different markets, I think, will have different people,
different products being taken up in Kenya, Nigeria and some of these markets.
Are you seeing a lot of business USDT accounts?
Yeah, it's not us.
That's just so much already.
Sub-Saharan Africa, I will club.
Sub-Saharan Africa does so much cross border settlement with Asia and a lot.
I want to say 70% of that settlement happens in USDT.
If I don't have my facts right.
And again, it's not official numbers that I'm getting.
But just based on what I know, 70% of that settlement happens in USDT.
So it's funny you say this.
We had launched MiniPay as a retail product.
And what we learned was some of these people that were settling B2B
settlements used to come and park some of their USDT on MiniPay
when it was just a product in the browser in Africa only,
because the yield on USDT on MiniPay was really high.
What was the yield?
It was a ridiculous amount, just on board.
And we were, again, for context, the average balance on MiniPay wallet
in Africa is between $10 plus minus.
So these balances aren't very high.
So when you give them like a yield of hypothetically 25% per annum or more,
that yield is not too much for the retail user.
But when you look at it from a commercial perspective,
if you're getting 25% on a dollar denominated stablecoin, that's a lot.
Nobody's giving you 25% yield on the dollar.
And so we saw a bunch of people park their money,
like the B2B settlers and cross-border payments guys,
some of their money into MiniPay accounts.
And then we were like, oh, we're going to have cap
upper limits to balances for this yield activity.
But it was great to see people found it very organically.
And are you seeing financial products come on chain
in those local economies?
Yeah. So I'll give you an example.
We have a protocol in the ecosystem called Heraka that does.
So, again, I'm a really big proponent of meet users where they're at
and not give them like, hey, this is a solution we've come up with.
You don't have to fit your behavior to this solution.
And so in these regions, for instance,
sacos or savings and lending groups are very popular.
And they're called different things in India.
They're called kitties.
And in Kenya, they're called sacos.
And these groups are very prevalent across emerging markets.
And so we have a protocol in the ecosystem called Heraka,
which does micro loans and then now starting savings.
So essentially, it's just like a savings and lending group
where you save and lend within a specific user group.
So you, me and three of our friends form a group and we save
and lend within each other.
And that's how it's done.
It's behavioral that's happened across generations in these regions.
And so when you bring that behavior on chain, it becomes really easy.
Then you can do settlement.
You can do accounting. Everything is on chain.
So Heraka, I think, is a really good example of that.
We're seeing people do employee payments.
There's a protocol called Franklin that is doing stablecoin payments for payroll.
One of my favorite examples that just came online
in the ecosystem is this protocol called Bando.
And you can buy gift cards to places like Target, Chipotle,
Starbucks in the US, but very specific to even the regions that we service.
So in Kenya and South Africa, you can get a gift card to ShopRite,
which is the target of that region.
And they have similar things in South America.
So really interesting products are coming on chain.
Some of them financial, some of them non-financial.
I'm going to give a shout out of one specific product
that is non-financial that I'm very fond of in the ecosystem.
It's a music streaming app called a Bando.
So think of it like Spotify.
The reason it's on MiniPay right now is because you can pay on a daily basis.
You can take a daily subscription.
And again, for you and me, this seems ridiculous.
Like, why would I want a daily subscription to a music streaming app?
But for some of the regions that we're talking about,
the monthly music streaming subscription is really expensive.
So there's some days you can afford it and some days you can't afford it.
And so the fact that you can break it down to such minute levels
and do it on chain with a little bit of a stable coin is really interesting.
And in Bando, if you guys are listening, has excellent music.
It's Afrobeat. I love it.
It's what's playing in the background when I'm doing deep focused work.
But really great.
We're constantly thinking about on chain financial.
But like when some of these use cases come online where you're like,
hey, there's a music streaming app that I could pay with stable coins.
That's cool.
I want to ask you one more question as we close out here,
which was given all this framing you've offered,
I'm a major believer that where we'll see value in this on chain economy
is in these real use cases, real assets.
Do you think blockchain platforms, applications need to have native tokens
or tokens for themselves?
Do you think that we need to have these,
I would call them internet money tokens that the industry has been known for
for a long time?
Or do you think eventually that fades into the background?
Funny you call them internet money.
My mom calls it magic bean money.
So I don't know whether we should have them or not.
I know that in my ecosystem, the seller token is there for decentralized
governance, and I think that's really, really critical.
I think one of the things that we're trying to do in some form or the other,
and whether you explicitly say it or not, is rebuild
how any organization works or how financial systems work.
That's why we're all in Web3.
We're trying to reimagine some of this.
I think decentralized governance is one of those areas.
But I'm really like, this is a really cool thing.
I believe in collective intelligence.
And so decentralized governance is a really good example of collective intelligence.
So the seller token, honestly, one of the big primary reasons
to have seller token is decentralized governance, where the ecosystem
and everybody in the community decides what is the future for the chain.
So, for instance, to give you a really good example,
we went from a layer one blockchain to a layer two blockchain.
We successfully migrated to a layer two blockchain.
But every single decision for the infrastructure was done in public
through decentralized governance.
And so every stack put out massive forum proposals
on the seller forum to say, hey, this is why you should pick us.
So we had proposals from OBStack, from Arbitrum, from Polygon ZK,
from Matterlabs and things like that.
And there was such an incredible healthy discussion in the community around
which stack we should pick.
So it wasn't centralized decision.
It wasn't seller foundation or C-Lab taking the decisions.
It's the community came together.
And I think some of the things that came up in some of those community decisions,
I was like, oh, wow, we weren't even thinking about this.
And so I think collective intelligence is really, really interesting.
Also, what it did was we've heard from different sources.
If you're picking a layer two stack, seller forum is like Wikipedia.
People actually go into the best seller forum to look at, oh,
when they're doing a stacking decision, they go into seller forum and look at,
oh, these are the things that were discussed.
This is what the answers were.
So I think decentralized governance is a really good example
of why you need native tokens or magic bean money.
Do I think we need as many as we have right now?
I think there will be a world of consolidation,
but I don't know when that world will be. But it's interesting.
We were talking about collective intelligence.
I think one of the reasons we specifically have been successful
as an ecosystem is because we have regional DAOs also.
So we have a DAO in Africa.
We have a Latam DAO.
We have a Thailand DAO.
We have a Philippines DAO.
And because we think that every region should have a say
in how we represent in that region.
And these DAO communities have been incredible
and also very active in our governance process.
And so as we're thinking about how do we do a go-to-market strategy
for that specific DAO, it's been really helpful to have the communities
in there have a massive say in some of those decision-makings.
I'm a big proponent, again, of decentralized governance.
I know it has some flaws.
We've all experienced some flaws at decentralized governance.
But I think overall, if you're able to manage it,
I think incredible concept and excited to see where it by balls
in the next five years.
I guess if you're going to have a digital financial system
or monetary system, you should have some form of
democratic monetary decision-making.
A hundred percent. We're a hundred percent aligned on that.
Well, Isha, thank you for coming on.
Hope you come back to chat with us again soon.
Thank you all for having me.
This was a lovely conversation.
I'm excited to see where this podcast grows and scales.
Thank you. Appreciate it.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island.
To find out more about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc.
To listen to all of our podcast episodes,
please go to onthebrink-podcast.com
or just click on the tab in our website.
Thanks for listening.